so recently when I was talking with
people in sad DEA I
um was asking and giv some examples of
how to talk to your
mind how to
communicate well you were there so you
don't answer the questions so
basically if
we say if we remember that the mind is
the wild animal that's been contained
and now hopefully being
trained how do you start talking to it
how do you start communicate him with
it so that it basically does what you
tell it to
do not other way
around so how would you talk talk to
it with wishing things
make it make it go along your
wishes like you wish your mind to not be
upset would that make it not
upset so you can't talk to it directly
basically in know words he doesn't
understand you so how would you be
conveying the messages you want to
convey give some
examples um what you kind of let it get
into so to speak sorry what you let it
like get into so to speak
so I mean yeah coest example is the
precepts you don't let it do that um
these things so course course forms of
communication would basically be the
precepts already not not letting it
right you can kind of carry that on to
um like just because it wants
I was thinking about this the other day
I'm not not so sure how to put it
but like the fact that there is
something present like a thought kind of
a pressure to think about something for
example um that thought is there but there is
um that thought is there but there is
the kind of extra step of the mind being
able to
like like you need to basically give it
permission to
um start thinking about these
things uh yeah but that still kind of
comes on the same level isn't it just
restraint it's not letting it or letting
it so precept sense restraint would
be forms of indirect communication so
you you are broadly cly conveying a
certain message so the Mind still
doesn't know
why the animal hasn't learned for
itself why it shouldn't be going in
those directions pursuing those
pressures he just knows that it can't go
there so how do you explain to it
why how do you tell a
dog how do you get the dog to prefer to
stay rather than to go
rather than to
resist well I mean you can punish it or
you can reward it I'm just speaking of a
dog I'm not entirely sure how that would
translate but well no we're speaking about the
but well no we're speaking about the
mind right I just gave the example might
more
pable so how do you punish the mind how
do you reward it do you need to punish
it when do you need to punish it
right that's that's right that seems not
correct well it's not incorrect
mhm it's the same
principle it is an animal
that's doesn't speak a
language so you make it see
something as you said through a reward
obviously you can just give it a treat
because they would be well they'll be
undoing your
training so how do you reward your
mind so it starts to see for itself so
that you are not doing
anything cuz the whole point obviously
the whole point of this I mean I think
we said before but it doesn't
matter um
the M it's the mind that
craves and you're the one that
experiences the results of that pain
well mind suffers as well but it's
unaware of it much like an animal would
not have enough
self-awareness so the Mind
craves but then you get to pay the price
for that with the suffering that's
felt so you can say oh I don't want to
Crave and I let go of craving but you're
not the one doing the craving you are
not holding holding the craving because
if you were you would let it go
instantly you would not need the W
teaching to tell you
that so it's just the mind the Mind
keeps the Wild dog
keeps biting the burning embers cuz he
doesn't know anything better cuz he
thinks that will destroy them and free
from the pain and you the one being
burned by
that so how do you tell that animal how'
you teach it to stop doing it
obviously precepts establishment in
virtue it's it's not negotiable because
that would be containing the animal they
will be like putting up a fence around
so that at least you know where the
animal is cuz you're not going to be
issuing any commands right or wrong if
you let the animal loose if it's
gone now obviously you have contained it
but if that's all you did well it's
still not tamed so it's still going to
be sure it probably not going to inflict
as much suffering as if somebody who is
immoral and not
virtuous but nevertheless still a wild
animal there is still plenty of um
opportunities within the fenced area to
to Crave to do stuff and then you would
feel pain on account of it so you want
it to know for
itself the craving is bad
that's when the suas when it says like
when the when the monk becomes an
Arun and his mind is tamed fully
completely freed from any possibility of
craving it says oh it's liberated and he
knows it is liberated he knows that
animal is
liberated that's it's like that kind
of um two teer knowledge so to speak
like yes he knows for himself but he
also knows that this thing there that
he's paired with is
liberated it's unable to
Crave so he cannot have any
fear or concern amidst things even that
are unpleasant even death like you know
among death he doesn't tremble cuz he
knows the dog is incapable of doing that
ever again and thus he can never again
again and thus he can never again
experience suffering as a result of
that so it's like the most immediate uh
knowledge so how do you teach it to stop
craving so let's look at it practically
so you
restrained you keep the
precepts you come Cross or you come near
the the mind the animal through your
moods through your feelings through the
pressures what do you do what do you
tell it
then I mean you can tell it drop it or
what not
but that might not necessarily
work to what what would be the first
thing you would have to
do say your mind bothers you so
something something's bothering you
there pressure annoyance ill
will what message you want to tell your
mind yeah keep digging keep biting this
it will go away then and we both will be
free or or no what do you
say just going to
unresisted down by you you're not you're
not trying to fight it you relax mhm
yeah and when that thing calms down it's
down it's
relaxed and you're finding a relaxing
situation but do you need to wait for it
to calm down or is
there what you tell me no I don't think
there like you I mean initially maybe
yeah you need to just kind of contain it
and say okay I'm not going to like it's
not allowed don't allow it
to think further in this direction for
example but is it the animal that's
thinking what is it
you well I I'm kind of not used to
thinking in terms of this me and the
mind that's what we getting used to okay
obiously well there's a reason for that
so cuz that is the point I mean the
Buddha did say the is that you can be
like even an outsider can completely
experience this passion towards the body
and remove any ownership but he can't do
it towards the Mind why because it it's
been so close to him for so long and
he's been appropriating for so long but
it's exactly the same
thing it's a phenomenon in your
experience that you just look past and
assume yourself to be but it's not
uh so the original question was
um okay so you don't do you need to wait
well I think before we now go to the
original question let's go to what is
the Mind here now so I I asked the the the
Mind here now so I I asked the the the
other question was basically so are you
doing the
thinking or is the animal doing the
thinking who's doing the thinking
it really depends what you're referring
to by the Mind CH I refer to CH yeah
that's the
animal you're taming CH you're not
taming anything else CH is the one
liberated
so so who's doing the thinking where
does the thinking come
from from you well by thinking you don't
referring to by
everything else is not
CH yeah the thoughts would arise but
then you
would overthink them or
intend further upon them mhm
uh because you don't see
the the first arising so to speak well
well the phen
phenomenon well first of all it's like
you allow it to be you're absorbed with
something like that's the first thing
and then you like then you think further
on account of being already like not
aware of attending to certain thing yeah
of attending to certain thing yeah
that's again say like you stop that you
would stop that but it's now let's say
you're acutely
pressured uh like let's give a practical
example somebody who know you full of
well you have thoughts of Cruelty towards
you have thoughts of Cruelty towards
that
person are you thinking those thoughts
or is the Mind think or is CH thinking
those thoughts what are those thoughts
who is who's responsible for them you so
you are you fully so what's the chi as
relationship to
that the pressure to think those
thoughts exactly so the dog is pressure ing you
exactly so the dog is pressure ing you
but you don't have to think
that that's why that whole like sabasa
about um well all the tains when it comes to
um well all the tains when it comes to
these um no sorry that's notas is it the
one about you know the master of thought
which is
that uh yeah 19 20 what was the
title um stilling of thoughts or
something something but it's go on and
maybe I can well yeah there all points
of like refining your thoughts thinking
the opposite thoughts you know yeah
that's see that's I keep saying to
people if you're doing that because
you're trying to get rid of the thoughts
means you're not even seeing your mind
to begin with you're blaming the
thoughts for the problem and then you're
trying to get rid of them by you know
sensuality think auba um hatred think
love or something but like you're not
seeing your mind you're doing it because
you're blaming the thoughts so first you
have to not try to get rid of the
thoughts that's the first message you give to the
that's the first message you give to the
pressuring
dog no see it bars at you cuz it also
thinks that the thoughts are the problem
thoughts are scaring the animal so the
animal is barking at the
thoughts and if you go along with it
well you're affirming what the animal is
craving
against so by convey the message of no
thoughts are not the problem I will
endure them so that the animal can see
some space between its own rage and the
thoughts but the animal is not thinking
the thoughts you
are so that's why then by not trying to
get rid of the thoughts by enduring the
pain of the mind you also get to see
where the pain comes from in case you
didn't have that view clarified
beforehand which is the pain comes from
the animal that pressures and craves not
the thoughts so then why would you think
thoughts so then why would you think
auba instead of sensuality what would be
the right reason to do
so teach the mind how to not present
that how to to teach the
mind how to see things right basically
yes yeah to basically to to calm it down
so the mind is excited in regard to this
thing well in regard to the same thing
you show it the ugly aspects you know I
say the dog wants to have what's in the
bag and it's really losing its Mind Over
It Well you show it what's in the bag
and it's in the bag and what's in the
bag is something absolutely disgusting
that he doesn't want to eat and then he
like okay no sorry and he will walk away
and lose interest in it so that's why
you're doing it so all those methods
quote unquote of countering the thoughts
you're not countering the thoughts
you're you're just broadening basically
the context of perspective exactly of
the very thoughts so the animal doesn't
go go in the direction he wants to go
same with
hatred cuz it's the mind of um meta not
not you you are not thinking mattera you
want mind you want the dog to be in the
state of unperturbed
friendliness so if you have like
thoughts of ill will pressured towards
thoughts of ill will by the animal well
you brought in the context show show it
the thoughts of the Peril of ill will
the unsatisfactory the the the
limitations and then the mind will like
oh yeah it's not really worth it so the
mind will drop it you don't need to drop
anything so is it like I was just trying
I was trying to kind of think how to put
it would be
the what a way of describing how how to
teach the mind in a general
sense because what the Mind wants when
it craves is peace basically what it's
after is peace but it is going about it
the wrong way because that's all it
knows exactly and so what you need to
know first is where peace actually comes
from yeah you need to learn that
yourself so you need to understand where
the peace comes from and then like you
can use basically any of these specific
things like auba like in regard to
sensuality or any of them would pertain
to where the peace actually is yeah uh
like kind of teaching the mind and okay
in this instance the peace is not in the
direction of sensuality peace is
actually in the direction of un
sensuality of discussion well see you
answer the question I was going to ask
that's basically what the uh treat is
that's the
reward you can't give it sensuality as a
reward because I said that will just
agitate further but fundamentally
exactly even chitt wants peace that's
why it pressures towards resolution of
central desire or ill will or any
hindrance so if you learn what the
actual piece is I what that right
balance is which you would have learned
through simply not trying to get rid of
thoughts or blaming them or blaming
external circumstance and being able to
endure things on the right level then
when the animal say say is agitated you
presented the the other side of the same
thing it comes down and that's where you
show it look there is a reward tell it
yeah you tell it that's a reward you do
the you do the basically the audible
sign sound with with what happen so it
starts to associate too like the dog
because you use a clicker CU like
initially that's the thing it won't even
you w necessarily and he want know where
to stop cuz you don't know where where
the peace is you don't know what's
actually peaceful but if you do know
what's peaceful you'll see when the
animal is within that piece and then you
can tell it and you do that sufficient
amount of time and it will start to see
for itself then you don't need a clicker
itself then you don't need a clicker
anymore because fundamentally yes
exactly he doesn't want to
Crave and it once I was thinking that's
like what you Rel relates to what you
said as well about the AR when he knows
it's liberated
like cuz when you're restraining and
everything it
um you know from one point of view
you're putting like a you're kind of
chaining it down and tying it down but
really kind of fundamentally it's the
animal that's chained from the start
like he kind of
chained in regard to well because it
craves it can't help craving so it's
kind of it's not liberated in that sense
it's bothered I wouldn't use I wouldn't
say it was already chained no you chain
it through through precepts and sensory
straint you fence it off guess but it's
it's already
agitated like the wild the wild elephant
the Wild dog whatever whatever animal
you want to use for this
contemplation it's wild and that's what
it means basically impulses are
controlling it it acts out of craving it
avoids pain it seeks pleasure and it's
absolutely oblivious to neutral
feeling so it would be fine if if it if it were
so it would be fine if if it if it were
not your problem but the point is
whatever that animal does you are the
one who's going to feel
it so it's like oh so then it is in my
best interest and Animal's best interest
to train
it to teach it how to not crave
and that's why the the whole like well
obviously that's why like nothing
nothing can match the pleasure of
Liberation or like satapati anagami
arant because it doesn't come it's not like
because it doesn't come it's not like
you engage with the senses and then you
get like a sort of a pleasant
feedback it's like completely not your
own doing it's the animal that stop
craving but obviously you fully
understand that it's entirely your own
doing cuz
no wild animal by any stretch by any
realm can sort of uh calm itself down in
a sense of remove the craving remove the
impulse and acting out of it that's
inconceivable CU it s
perpetuating anyway pick an animal in
the world doesn't matter if it looks
peaceful internally every animal what's
in common to that such animal realm in
general it has to act out of
impulse which means means it's has not
enough capacity for that reflection
where it can understand its own doing
its own input so you teach
it and now it's
completely liberated which means now it's
liberated which means now it's
completely impossible for
you by any stretch to experience even
possibility of
suffering because the so reason for
suffering was the animal craving that's
it and even more obviously as the Su to
say it will be impossible for you to be
tied to another animal ever
again so that's how you reward it you
reward it by thinking thoughts of the
factual peace at the right
peace at the right
time not you can be thinking them
blindly as a method but as with the dog
training the timing is important that's
where you make an
association could could you also say
that it's the um
teaching the value of neutral feeling
only when neutral feeling arises no not
obviously preempting it but yes yeah
well that's exactly that's what you
you're setting up a neutral
feeling and then click come through de
agitating the animal yes through calming
it down through through
basically not acting out of the pressure
that animal is putting on
you and then exactly when there is a
neutral feeling
established you show that that factual
recognition you think it you recognize
it cuz obviously any anything you see
smell taste touch and
think is what animal
experiences so that's that's where your
responsibility comes in oh you know if
if everything is already anata then
nobody Kills Nobody no you are doing
it so you choose sight sound smell taste
touches thoughts which means you choose to keep
thoughts which means you choose to keep
the animal wild or tame it on account of
following suitable s sound smell taste
touches or unsuitable as a su
says so by thinking factually thoughts
of restraint
relinquishment um withdrawal from un
wholesome the benefit of that you are
putting those things in front of an
animal so you are familiarizing it with
it so it will it will um it will get to
see it it will get get to learn it it
will get to associate it for itself and
that's when you know your work is done
when you don't have to keep putting it
now the Animal also
prefers non
craving uh non agitation and so on and
then it's like okay my work's done
now this tendency
to ignore the neutral feeling it
undermines that
reward like the ability to well yeah I
mean becoming indolent towards but
that's whose tendenc is
that yours or animals mine
exactly so stop ignoring it yeah
and that's you could understand now on
the Bas of we described how like was it
uh it was gotam wasn't it was his mother
and she came and asked for a brief
instruction to go into the forest for
the Vasa he says whatever you know it's
it's unsuitable un wholesome don't do it
basically don't engage with it whatever
you know it's holesome engage with
it it's like if you stick to that on the
level of body speech mind I S sound
smell taste touches
thoughts well it will be highly
unlikely virtually
impossible that the animal is not
tamed because see it's it it's
Wilderness it needs fuel it needs
maintenance it needs perpetuation so and
you doing it through carelessly
attending to unsuitable S sound smell
taste touches
thoughts so if you you stop carelessly
attending to those things and whenever
those things pop up out of your own
mental habits well you don't lose the
context you don't lose
Yara you broaden the context by
presenting the bigger picture and then
the animal starts to learn oh whenever
it's this it's this thus it calms down
it stops craving and you will know when
it stops
craving you will know when the dog
listens to you like you don't need to H
how does this happen now let me Psych
about
it that's also mind you this is not
really relevant but it's kind of
interesting suppose like in the sutas when when say
suppose like in the sutas when when say
all the a abandon the animal is thing
there are no more kind of underlying
tendences there when it says like if he were to
there when it says like if he were to
direct his
mind towards the memory of the previous
lives and if there is an opening he will
remember it he's not doing the remembering you
it he's not doing the remembering you
are not doing that you just tell your
mind to go and
fetch what the same with any and the dog
just goes and go runs and you wait and
comes back after and it fetched some
memorabilia that now you remember
exactly it's the same with any memory so
people already deep down can have a hint
of the animal that's not they're doing
so to speak how do you remember so
remembering like what I ate today well
yeah how' you remember it try to
remember something that that you haven't
already thought before you said
it TR try to remember something what I
yesterday what did you know what did you
did what did you do 10 years ago just
remember it
yeah did you come up with the m or did
you just sort of 10 years ago and then
the memory was presented to
you yeah exactly every single time
especially when you can't remember
something and you're trying that's when
you realize how much it's not you're
doing you're and then if you try too
hard that becomes a thing now that's
obstructing the animal from actually and
it's like no I have to try a bit and
then you remember in other words then
the the animal remembers it for you
so who is that you I keep talking
about so we have determined the animal
is what
is who is this you that is
responsible for what you feed to the
animal what you present it with to
to
di well yes but how would if Su refer to
it what would what Su call that the
that the
individual individual would be exactly
it would be like the collection say of
all of it s SM touches thoughts but this
specific sense of
you your point of
view what is that in terms of the suta
classifications and terminology what
would that what would the closest thing
to that
be five clinging agregates more specific Mana
specific Mana
yeah you were guessing that was the
first thing that came to my mind it is
it's intellect yeah that's exactly why d
d says that Mano is the Forerunner of
everything un wholesome not
CH because you realize well yes sure
wholesome and wholesome craving comes
from CH on account of what Mano has been
feeding it what Mano has been thinking
what images he has been revolving around
that is what's going to reflect back
onto the animal and that's what's going
to be looking at
so there you go finally the difference
between CH and Mano has been
cleared so and for all once and for
all so
so so let's now say so where is the
animal in your own experience how do you
cuz see you can't think the
animal you you think you CH but that's
obviously images which is
mano so how do
you relate how do you reveal how do
you connect with with the where do you look
connect with with the where do you look
for it n h
n okay but see the mood is something
you're
perceiving being aware of the general
attitude in regards to whatever you are
attending to or doing and where would
that be how would you be aware of the general
attitude by reminding yourself of
bringing it to
mind but the at would that be something
you're holding no that's the that's why I'm
holding no that's the that's why I'm
saying it would be how you would relate
to the chitt because it's something that
is on the level of CH the attitude give
me some examples of the attitude any CRA
any graving well yes theoretically any
craving any gases in chitt but I'm
asking how do you where do you find that
chitt attitude of distance
you're saying in the back of him where
the back where's your
mind so what I'm asking is say somebody
asks you how do I find my mind how do I
you how do I find my mind how do I
reveal it cuz obviously if you think
it it's the thoughts you're
thinking so attitude yes
but attitude how do I contemplate
attitude how do I contemplate
attitude how do I reveal my mind on kind
of an
attitude I think is there more direct
way you know that's what I'm
okay where the kind of discomfort is in
a way not like obviously that needs some
clarification but so where the feeling
is yeah so what's
felt oh the mind is not the
feeling but it can be found apart from
it Clos so how do you then get to even
more directly to that can be found apart
from feeling on account of feeling
feeling
physicality yeah in a way yeah
what is what we refer to as physicality
IE mindfulness of your form
internally what does that
do again in regard to revealing your
contrast between say that way suppos
so then if you have say if you have
physicality like mindfulness of the body
internally mindfulness of that
physicality internally and
feeling
felt not just s
about where's a CH there but
between between what in that
relationship yeah I mean the fact that
there is a
relationship well what what what what
does what kind of relationship is that
a unfounded I mean theoretically it's an
un I mean it's a one that requires
interrogation okay but that's irrelevant
then for where is
so what part of the relationship is
relevant for which it is so your
physicality and your
feeling can help you discern
peripherally because you can't think it
directly
CH on account of what you discern
that so don't think it feel the feeling
experience the physicality
are you referring to resistance no no
okay didn't think didn't think so but
you could there could be another
approach but no I'm not I'm not say
there a neutral feeling they're not
resisting anything where is J
anything where is J
there so like now as we're talking about
it experience in the physicality
internally feeling the feeling
what else is
there not theoretically what else is
there specifically in your experience is
it something
else what what type of feeling is
it Pleasant unpleasant
neutral so the about intention sorry
intention well yes it is intention but I
want I want people to
come to that conclusion in their own
description and the
words so if physicality
reveals or basically experiencing
physicality internally sets you resets
you into your
situation the the general experience as
a whole the framework of it but you
can't be outside of the present moment
quote unquote feeling being
felt and then what else what else are
you having there pressure towards okay
so why is the pressure
there towards what on account to
what well there would be if there's
pressure it would be to like let's say
intend something
do something on account of a perception
something that you're something that
you're attending to on account of for
example okay I don't know he's asking me
this question I must give an answer okay
for example so where's your CH there in
that example you still not telling
me de pressure it's not
press sure it's closest to it but I'm
asking even more directly accurately oh
like for somebody who just started
pressing their mood is their CH they
don't see anything else subtler than
that but obviously the more you do it
it's not the pressure it's
not so how do you see that which is
invisible well you have to see both like
if there's the feeling and the let's say
if there's a pressure yeah okay to
intense so you see both exactly
so you see both exactly
and and then seeing kind of well the
chit is basically like the space quote
unquote in between the two that's how I
put it yeah and it doesn't need quote
unquote that
is the space is neither the space
created through neither here nor
there and the reason why that's
important is because you can be seeing
the two and and then coming up to see
the third and you're not going to see
the third it's going to fall on one of
the two so in order to see chitt then you
two so in order to see chitt then you
need
to undo maybe 50 60 maybe 80% of your
craving to see the chitt in order to see
it it depends depends how strongly you
want to see
chitt it's the absolute probably
most accurate cleanest
y you can have principles over here and
there but when it comes to in the chah
that is the only like there is anything
coarser than that cannot will not reveal
it it will reveal the hints of it the
signs of the mind you know the Sim of
the cook again beforehand but the point
is you want to be able to directly know
where it is wherever whenever and
wherever it is in that that sense so
that's when you're
always well keeping an eye on the dog
which means now you can have even more
accurate timing for your instructions
for your commands for your
clickers so basically in order to see
chitta you need to see both physicality
and feeling and then probably endure
that for a while until your own craving
to see the Chet subsides
and it would subside because although
you're not seeing the chah
directly by enduring the physicality
experience in the physicality with a
currently enduring feeling that is a
message you convey to the cheetah that
will basically calm me down even if
you're not seeing
it and then you see it
can we speak a little bit more about the
physicality I think I've been
overthinking that these past few
days so what's your body posture now
sitting you didn't have to stand up to
tell me that no is there an eternal
internally felt
fact of that seated
body yeah kind of there is the fact that
I'm sitting but internally in internal
sense of it like I mean on the inside
let's say that on the inside right but I
mean when that fact that I'm sitting
sorry like the fact that I'm sitting
with don't it's not the fact that you're
sitting it's the internal fact
of your
sitting or the internal fact that's
revealed through recognizing the fact of
your external sitting let's put it that
way so you're seated you cannot possibly
doubt that maybe find a different word
for it you could doubt how to express
it but that fact you can doubt
but how do you know
that can you tell me you're seated even
if you close your
eyes even if you're not looking
externally at your seated
body so what are you telling me then
what are you what are you seeing when
you close your eyes and I say what's
your body
posture how do you well let me ask like
this close your eyes and I'll ask you do
you have a
body yes how how do you know that where
did that knowledge come
from it's just there I guess just
something that I
remember well speak you remembered it
where was it before you were remembering
it was it
elsewhere can it be elsewhere can it be
anywhere else but right there
yeah I mean no impossible you can be
everywhere else you can forget about it
distract yourself go to great extents
but whenever you remember it you find it
where it always was that's the
physicality the internal side of that
mhm not your Associated images with it
which of course are going to follow when
you think of your body you're going to
have images of that but as I said even
the general question do you have a
body you already know the answer to that
so do I have a
body and then look at that internal fact
of that thing there what we
described two talks ago maybe last one
the intern internal gravity or whatever
you want to call it there is a
physicality that is the situation that
is the the the the the framework for
every other sub subsequent experience
you might have on account of your
senses it's kind of the being embodied
so to speak that's kind sure yeah you
can say that way yeah so the the point
of this is that it's not to like
externally observe your body but to
discern that internal one and that's the
whole setan of body within the body yeah
you start thinking the body and find the
body experience the body within your
thoughts of that body and when that
become your thoughts of the body
experience further internal body in
regard to those thoughts of body to the
extent necessary for the final knowledge
I think that's kind of what I
was like just that the tendency of kind
of getting the idea of like oh mental
image that's how it works everything has
to basically be an image like that but
the point
is through Discerning them rightly you
won't take them for granted that that's
it cuz there is the factual
physicality always at that same place so
to speak at that same
space that you are
experiencing so in that sense I know
it's not obviously accurate strictly
speaking but yes you can feel that yeah
as opposed to think it but yeah like you
were saying earlier that that feeling is
always experience what so yeah I just basically
experience what so yeah I just basically
repeating what I was what you just said
in the sense that feeling you mean the
body is always experience yeah of course
yeah that experience of that internal
body is always there and it's just being
covered up regardless of the mood
regardless of the pressure regardless
regardless regardless it's the it's it's
the container let's put it that way so
that it's the basis for all of you as I
said particular s sound smell taste
touches thoughts
that that would
be like taking the pressure for example
as the sign of the as the mind but then
not that that they will be taking the
pressure sorry yes um that's all right
the the
uh uninterrupted of feeling feeling
would be yeah less perturbed the more
that yeah this
uh practice of of
of Discerning the relationship between
physicality of body and well yeah but
see like you're not you're only
Discerning the
relationship marginally really it's not
about the relationship it's not about
Discerning it in the sense of figuring
it out how it relates it relates by
being there these two things are there
that's the relationship so yes you do
need to discern that CU for as long as
you think it it relates is in the L
comes from here here into there and then
it goes elsewhere yes of course you're
you're not going to see anyway but if
you're recognizing the just
mere just the
position of the internal physicality and
feeling felt that's the relationship you
want but not what of course discern and
then really uh not cover
up even if it's neutral well especially
yeah EX that's the whole point so yes
you could say there's physicality and
there's a neither pleasure nor pain felt
great so don't cover up that experience
now and that's you know I was saying
before and any if you have thoughts okay
but where is my Che include that in the
experience of those two
things don't give into it they try to
resolve it you're closer to resolution
by not acting out of that craving then
by acting out of that but of course it
was that very craving that brought you
there if you didn't crave to see the
chitt if you were not pressed towards it
if you did not generate a desire to do
so well you would have not have you
would have not
um discern the relationship between the
internal physicality and feeling
so it's kind of like you know how the
aggregate of virtue sets up a fence
around the wild animal well this is kind
of like a um another sort of
um layer to
it so you might not know at
times where my mind is or discern it
peripherally correctly but you know physicality and
correctly but you know physicality and
the feeling so you know what it has to
be within that
space that's why the space was
relevant cannot be outside of this
impossible in the same sense well I
don't know where my moods come from and
what they are and how they act and how
they pressure me but I know they cannot
pressure me on a kind of household life
they canot pressure me account
sensuality ill will of this course
nature in of the precepts they cannot
because those things have been
abandoned back to this
physicality if you look at uh Mima 62
you see like uh the Buddha teaching
rahula and before gets to
hanati he's talking about the five AGS
are not not yours so that's what you
must see them as but then he goes to the
elements but with specific bodily
contemplation so it's like whatever is
internal that is hard and
solid weight
weight
gravity and taken
up that is the Earth element
and and it's like they have the
head you have that it it gives you that
idea have the head that thought have the
body Nails teeth and it's like to me that
Nails teeth and it's like to me that
that's it's you got to find that
internal hard solid
corresponding aspect you have an idea of
hair of the head
M where's the corresponding hardness of
it is that where's the hardness where's
the solidity or the weight of
it is it you can't you know you can have
the idea of the
word and the concept yeah what is the
internal
solidity of it not external CU somebody
be touching the hair or something no
internally so you want to include all
those images in that internal solidity
and why is that
important now what we're talking about
it why is it important to say see all
the fates as not mine or all the form
fates as not mine or all the form
internal
external earth water fire air to leave
nothing out why is that important to
include it in that relationship of
physicality felt
whatever is left out is taken up as mine
automatically but in terms of what we
talking about CH why is it relevant for
that yes of course taking his mind but
in terms of this whole
talk why is it want to include
everything we to include it all within
the relationship
or yes well relationship established as
I said and then whatever it's left out
you realize cannot be left out so then
you intentionally unleaving It Out by
bringing it up on the basis of
physicality felt actually that's a relationship
felt actually that's a relationship
isn't it physicality felt that's I don't
need to say experience physicality and
feel the Feeling Just physicality felt
both are already
there so why is it important
to include things they were Des excluded
well is that is it that that's important
or just kind of if things are left out
then you're not seeing either end
properly well so to speak like that is
important but I guess this is so you are
seeing say you are factually experience
physicality feeling
felt but the suit encourages to start
including all these
seemingly less relevant
things all internal B and bones and
this why well to disassociate those
things from what from the internal
physicality well no you are kind of
associating with with internal
physicality first at least that's what you're doing
first at least that's what you're doing
they are disassociated from physicality
internally that's why they're left
out when you think innal physicality you
don't have the images of your bones and
Marrow and
stuff you hav an Associated them with
it okay I going from the other
direction so in the context of what
we've been talking about the Mind J the
animal why is it
important to include all these images
all these things all these
implicit why is it important to include
include the image with the physicality
so yeah like what you were describing
like oh any okay internally um body
experienced internally and starts
including the head the nails the the
extent of all of that internally why is
that relevant it's peaceful well let's
say it like this no again that doesn't
bear any answer to Chet that I'm asking
so what happens to Chet if you're not
including
it so if these things are not
included how does that
affect chit it's uh it's
uh it's
not expanded or it's right
orate it's not seen to the extent the
things are not included to that extent
you won't be seeing
it so you can think you're seeing
it but if the internal
extent of that
physicality is not brought
up to the certain size let's call it
that way you won't be seeing the mind
because mind is what's left when
everything else is
included of that
space that's why contemplation of
Infinite Space if you are defined to
perceive it immediately outlines where the mind
it immediately outlines where the mind
is cuz it won't be in anywhere in the
space so Infinite Space means any
possible direction of space up it
doesn't matter what axis you
take if you're perceiving that that
level you are clearly then outlining the
mind for what it's
not obviously as I said for somebody who
just starts practicing becoming aware of
their own thoughts including them as
real
phenomena everything else not that will
be the
chitt but yeah chitt has obviously
proliferated through your own
well through your own lack of
discernment that's the point and for as
long as chitt is not clearly outlined
internally through what it is
not there's going to still be an
underlying tendency to fall into the
tendency to fall into the
assumption that the pressure came from
here or there or this or
that that's the connection by the CH
can't enter your Mano in your world it's
animal is animal you are you but through
not fully delineating that not fully
fully delineating that not fully
understanding clearly the difference in
those two domains one is invisible
domain of the
animal um that's how you basically
yourself assume
project pressure coming out of the
thoughts or this or that it pertains to
you not the animal
like how we started
this when you
have anger you the thoughts to think
these pressure to think these cruel
thoughts we oh wa who who thinks the
thoughts was it you or the animal oh no
it's me due to the pressure exhibited by
the animal so there's going to be traces of
animal so there's going to be traces of
that pressure left for as long as
things are not sufficiently included
into that physicality felt here and
now and when they are then the mind is
how Su says you know abas and bright and
infinite and pure and
unobstructed still the animal still is
going to disintegrate like everything
else so you're not holding any mystical
views in regard to it but it's factually
clean obedient no more clickers no more
hints he just does the right thing on its own
he just does the right thing on its own
accord every single
time makes the right choice
and how would you know practically
speaking not from the other hand's point
of view how would you
know when on some days like you're are
not outlining your mind clearly
enough what would be the first symptom
of that
and it would remain throughout that
symptom it would
disappear hint we spoke about it in last
two talks
talks
suffering yeah of course but more more
practically resistance resistance
yeah of course suffering yes but you
know okay so I suffer do I
resist fighting the fight well fight
comes out of it fight comes out of
resistance so why is it important for
so why is it important for
you for your
mano to give up
resistance again in the context of CH
that we speak
about because it's not going to calm it
down it's not well exactly you just
punish exactly you can be telling it
what you want but if the dog sees that
you are the one resisting it well then
of course it will continue doing its own
resisting and craving against it yeah so
you don't add more of the same basically
yeah so you practicing the unresisting
of resistance in regard to what's felt
is another way of talking to your
mind however cely you might be doing
that you realize it's already conveying
the same message that I might be doing
you know in the future on a on a More
subtler Level doesn't
matter so here and now internal
physicality felt
unresisted then add few things to that
mix
push it into that framework include
those thoughts of this form and that
form and internal and body and Skin and
Bones and then unresisted and then
include more and then
unresisted the physicality yeah include
more into the
physicality or start contemplating
impermanence destruction sensation and
unresisted mhm that's also talking to
your mind that's also telling the
obvious to the
Mind danger danger exactly gratification
danger
escape it's really just presenting these
rightly seen
phenomena even if you don't see the Mine
by having them there the mind seeing
them you know I don't know where the dog
is I know it's within this fence cuz
fence is
impenetrable I don't know where it is
but if I play these sounds I know will
have to hear it it's like in the kind of
prodding the elephant with Spears and
swords and stuff the Su yes yeah yeah to
teach it how to not move even further
yeah I was thinking that could also be
um like we were talking a couple of
talks ago how do you Gladden the
mind um and that
actually maybe it's somewhat Less Direct
but I think bringing up like for example
you know things like thing concrete
things that would represent impermanence
for example and I'm resisting that is
kind of how to Gladden it further
basically it becomes you see well imag
again imagine like you're with a dog and
there is something there's a fact
agitating sight
mhm for both you and the dog and the dog
is just barking and losing it so you
can't remove the sight you can't even
tell to a dog that's actually there is
no danger cuz it's it's already agitated
so you just sort of you know P it and
show it show it physically that you are
calm and then the dog will Cal down
although the thing is still there and
you still might be edgy about it but it
would come down cuz you unresisted
yourself
so that was the relevance of you know
what he talking about in those previous
two talks was exactly that it's just
yeah you might not you don't you don't
necessarily see the animal that clearly
or not always and so on but factually by
unresisting yourself again as I said
theal has to hear it because you know
it's
there think in one of the older videos
you were talking
about just this kind
of I think it was in the context of just
kind of overthinking like oh what is the
body you just said it is just like the
actual body
there um at least that's that's how I remember
um at least that's that's how I remember
it it does seem like that's kind of
a pretty concrete way of just cutting
through the I mean of course you can
take that of help
ex but the point is to to look for it
and you realize oh I find it not by
finding it but by uncovering it cuz it's
already there right you're not making it
so there's a there's a sense of touch
like well and
now start with a sense of touch but then
you have to look past it that's the
closest and then as you can see like
bodily Sensations true true but that's
the but really it's not really closer to
the body internal body is Sal yeah as as
sights are yeah exactly exactly smells
smells are already touching it sounds
are already landing on it m that's it's
not more closer it's just that people
approach the body through the external
images of it so then see what I think my
body is it's this thing here and inside
of that is the sensations and touches
thus that must be more of the body M but
that's already completely upside down
like the whole idea of external it's on
the account of you already experiencing
that physicality here and now
that internally that that's the framework for
internally that that's the framework for
anything whether it's internal whether
it's external or then internal
again yeah I mean this I mean it's
something I was thinking a while ago but
like like at some point I remember
having the thought or realizing it's
kind of completely crudus to think that
like Through The Eyes I'm just I'm what
I'm perceiving is the room and then like
I'm perceiving my body with the sense of
touch and it's like I'm just as well
perceiving the room with my body yeah
exactly as no that's that's I think we
said it before and I think even in some
philosophies it was said all you are
perceiving is your senses perceiving
things so the the the space revealed
with your eyes is secondary to your EXP
experience of eyes seeing space revealed
objects but yeah the mind's through the
whole desire
non-restraint well not even as I said
not even recognizing thoughts and images
to be real as
such not seeing them as phenomena that's
how you then proliferate further into
that space and then that space
externally that you perceive becomes a
reference point back onto you or on you
or Al and then we are all equal filling
out this space but all of that
secondarily proliferate The Experience
what your experience is s well what your
experience is Eyes Ears Nose tongue Body
Mind perceiving sight sound smell taste
touches thoughts you are not you do not
have access to the sense
objects so that's what I kind of meant
earlier when I think um because I
thought when you were asking about like
including the um so I was wondering
about clarifying this anyway so that's
why I'm the specific I don't know organs
I'm the specific I don't know organs
like I don't know the hair on the head
or the
because because I think what I thought
you were referring to was let's say for
example um you you kind of start with these kind
um you you kind of start with these kind
of um like vague IDE or perceptions phys
like and they would be kind of tactile
perceptions like say I no perception of
feet or of knees or
whatever um
um
that kind of stand for the
body yeah
yeah
but but they're not the body or they're
not the internal body if they stand for
it they will be there and
then so that's what I mean like but
that's I don't know it seems to me that
they stand for it basically by not being
kind of fully discerned or not being
clearly discerned as images because like I if I
discerned as images because like I if I
look at basically I like and I'm kind of
saying this practically I'm not certain
this is not me like I well actually it
can't it's it can only be
ofage um and but then there there is
something else like behind or below it
so I think what I understood was
like it is kind of further clarifying or
Discerning more of the yes and there is
a need for that but also um that in and
of itself does not necessarily Translate
it it certainly removes the obstructions
and it probably
um is improving your communication with
the mind but in of itself does not
necessarily result what we've been talking about in
result what we've been talking about in
this talk yeah no this is this is
slightly gentle just but yes of course
yes like that whole casin practice as we
said before you could
before you could
eventually have images of the Great
element of Earth and planet and whatever
Universe mountains Stones the the
properties of it you can have images of
those properties associated with your
internal form with your internal body if
you would have diligently abandoned
everything else inferior to
it but the the another more like a
practical side of including the body
organs ke that's basically it is what
occupies the space of the body here you
just leave it out mhm and you judge as I
said the space of the body by the space
of your per so to
speak but if you recognize well the
space of the body space of the
perception space is there and it's fully
occupied to the brim MH San smell taste
touches images of what constitut San
smell taste touches there is nothing in
and out left in anymore okay
so where does where would
chitt where does a
CH correspond
to
approximately in terms of that space
that your body occupies
where would you place your
Chet the heart
yeah kind of in that area not
specifically to the left or
something why well who knows it's
relevant
that's why this whole contemplation of
these specific images like bones and
skin and
whatever you're kind of lighting up you
know you you yeah you're you're lighting
up you're lighting up the whole Kaya
yeah and it's like that first step of it
well you know yeah of course of course
experien the whole body by by lighting
of the whole Kaa you realize it's all
included does CH is not there so by
including everything that's how you
outline what's not there which is
CH actually sorry I'm now may be
slightly jumping but you said um but
that was something that also occurred to
me like the you were asking like where
would you place your
CH and it would be kind of corresponding
internal but I was thinking that could
also be
um what it's referring to with par mukam
or even more um sort of bringing the
well yeah I think there is an over there
of course yeah
anyway kind
of but yes there are
certain convergence
points convergence points of of your
own um body in its
entirety that untrained CH would be
preferring in other words means of
expression means of gaining pleasure
means of um acting
out and it would be let's say descending
upon those
parts like losing perspective in regard
to everything
else it's like you know I don't know
like violent people have that expression
like oh these hands have the mind of
their own like when they get angry and start
own like when they get angry and start
fight beating and as in like that just
that that's all they that's all they see
so it's like factually your mind would
have been probably descended on your
limbs or sexuality wise you're growing
yeah speech your mouth things that fact
taken up so by practicing un taking up
unresisting from your point of view not
making cheetah to do it you
unresisting those convergence
points send a message to
CH cuz it can't make
you double down unless you choose to
Double Down
so that's the stealing of
activations physical verbal and
mental stealing of taking
ups that you're doing they still going
to be taking up that the animals doing
but as I said you don't have to worry
about that if you untake up everything
you've been taken
up then the animal will not be able to
remain hold in for much longer